<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mono-pq.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mono-pq.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-08-14T02:45:39+00:00</updated><id>https://mono-pq.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple portfolio website and blog for a data analyst. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Identifying data anomalies</title><link href="https://mono-pq.github.io/blog/2023/detectinganomaly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identifying data anomalies"/><published>2023-03-17T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-17T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mono-pq.github.io/blog/2023/detectinganomaly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mono-pq.github.io/blog/2023/detectinganomaly/"><![CDATA[<p>One of my very first tasks as a data analyst was to familiarise myself with the data which the business is concerned about and try to observe if there is any data anomalies associated with them. This couldn’t be done without understanding the business processes and operations that the data is representing.</p> <p>At first, it seems as though it’s an impossible task given the open nature of the problem. There was little to no guidance where to start. Given that the entire project is newly hired, each of us has our struggles. No matter who you tried to ask, you realise that they know as little as you do.</p> <p>So how should I complete this task?</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/proj_work_1_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="data analytics" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/proj_work_1_2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="website" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_3-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_3-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_3-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/proj_work_1_3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="feedback" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Image credits: <a href="https://www.freepik.com">Freepik</a> and <a href="https://pixabay.com/">Pixabay </a> </div> <p>The most obvious one is to find out how to obtain access to the data which the business users depend on. Some questions that you could ask include:</p> <ol> <li>What type of data does the business generate and where is the data stored?</li> <li>Is there any data warehouse available where access could be granted for analysis purposes?</li> <li>What are business operations and processes and whether there is any documentations for reading and reference?</li> <li>Is there any upstream or downstream dependencies of the data? If so, how the process flow looks like?</li> </ol> <p>Of course, the questions above are non-exhaustive as it is highly dependent on your industry and area of work. However, it is a good starting point.</p> <p>Once you have gotten access to the data, you can give it your best attempt to extract the data from the systems or databases for your analysis. However, that is not an easy task by itself. Depending on your organisation setup, you might need to find out the data connection configuration to establish the connection for data extraction or find out the production url of the application where you could access the data. For certain industries, you might only be able to extract the data via a VPN or secured connection to prevent any unauthorised disclosure of the organisation’s proprietary information.</p> <p>So, now you should have access to extract the data. But should you dive right into it? I have tried doing so. Only to find out that the size of the data that I am dealing with is massive. Millions of records with over hundreds of columns. Where and how should I start?</p> <p>Start with understanding the business operations that the data represents and get hold of the metadata (which is data that describes data). This would help you get a sense of what type of data you are dealing with and what are some of the underlying assumptions that you need to be aware of (especially when working on the analysis). For instance, <em>start_time</em> can have multiple meaning in different contexts. In the context of a time-series, <em>start_time</em> might represent the start of the window. In the context of a calls dataset, it might represent the start of a call. With an understanding of the business and help of metadata, you get a better idea of what is the data you are dealing with. And this will help you to push your exploration deeper.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_4-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_4-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/proj_work_1_4-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/proj_work_1_4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="forest" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Image credits: <a href="https://pixabay.com/">Pixabay</a> </div> <p>Now, there is finally some light sipping through at the end of the dark tunnel. We can dive deeper into a subset of the large dataset to answer some fundamental questions relating to the business. When dealing with a massive dataset, it is important to ask targeted and focused questions relating to the business problems that we might want to solve. For example, instead of looking through the entire data, we just want to know how the business has been doing in the recent quarter (i.e., 3 months). By asking targeted and focused question, it helps us to increase the speed and effectiveness of the data extraction and analysis process. With targeted scope, it’s also easier to spot any anomalies that might be of interest to the business users. For instance, when querying the data for the latest query, you might find that the data is missing for the last month which might be an anomaly or a sudden dip in the revnenue which was not expected given your domain knowledge. That’d be a starting point to dive deeper using data or effective collaboration with the relevant stakeholders to find out the root cause.</p> <p>Yet, it’s ironic that understanding the business and have the awareness of potential anomaly (i.e., able to identify them from the data) have to come before even starting the actual work. This might be challenging especially when you are new to an industry without much domain knwoledge in the area of business that you are dealing with. However, challenge can always be overcome by proactively searching and reading through relevant documentation, talking to the right people about their business processes and keeping your ears and mind open during meetings with the keystakeholders. Information comes from anywhere. The more you expose yourself to different channels and platforms, the more you’ll learn.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="datascience"/><category term="datascience"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Illustrates how it is possible to identify data anomalies via data analysis]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Structured thinking for the role of data analyst</title><link href="https://mono-pq.github.io/blog/2023/structuredthinking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structured thinking for the role of data analyst"/><published>2023-03-04T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-04T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mono-pq.github.io/blog/2023/structuredthinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mono-pq.github.io/blog/2023/structuredthinking/"><![CDATA[<p>Structured thinking is one of the basic skills that data analyst needs to be equipped with. It helps you recognise the problem or situation, organise information, identify gaps and opportunities, and brainstorm potential options available.</p> <p>In an ideal world, perfect information and data could be available for each problem or task assigned. However, in practice, that wouldn’t be the case. For instance, you might be assigned a task with limited information such as <strong>“provide me with the accuracy of email alert received by users from the control tower by tomorrow”.</strong> Some might dive straight into the problem with an inherent assumptions of the type of email alert, period which the email alert was sent, and the control tower that is involved. Yet, all of these were not clearly specified in the instruction. If any of the assumptions are wrong, time and effort will be wasted on rework.</p> <p>In such situration, structured thinking can help you clarify the scope of work before starting on the task. It also helps align the expectations with your manager or stakeholder(s) who assigned the task to you.</p> <h3 id="1-clarify-the-context-based-on-the-limited-information-available">1. Clarify the context based on the limited information available</h3> <p>Context is important especially when you are working with data. It’s easy to go down a rabbit hole with endless possibilities and options based on the data. Hence, without understanding the context, you’ll often find it difficult to provide a reasonable recommendation to the stakeholders.</p> <p>In the above example, the context that needs to be clarify is as follows:</p> <ul> <li>What’s the underlying reason behind the analysis? Have our stakeholders flagged out problems relating to the alert accruacy of the control tower?</li> <li>If there is more than one control tower, which control tower should we focus on?</li> <li>Which email alert should we focus on?</li> <li>How is the email alert triggered? What’s the underlying logic for the trigger?</li> <li>Which period should we look back at (e.g., past week, past month, past 3 month, past year)?</li> <li>If you are dealing with multiple regions/countries, is there a specific region/country to focus on?</li> <li>In terms of alert accuracy, are we looking at whether the alert is valid based on the logic and data or are we looking at whether the potential missing alert that wasn’t flagged when the data reflects an incident/risk or something else?</li> <li>Is the request urgent? Is deadline negotiable? (This is especially important if you are already preoccupied with other tasks.)</li> <li>Is there any specified format of sharing the findings with the stakeholders?</li> </ul> <p>By asking some of these questions, you’ll be able to understand the context of the task, find out the relevant stakeholders who are involved and interested in your findings, and clarify the scope of the task. These information can help you better manage the expectations of your manager and the stakeholders and estimate the amount of work required for this task.</p> <p>Now that you have a better understanding of the problem and context, you’ll need to figure out what are the data and tools you require for your analysis, and whether you have access to these data and tools.</p> <h3 id="2-availability-of-information-data-and-tools">2. Availability of information, data and tools</h3> <p>It is not rare for you not to have access to the information, data tools required for the task. Furthermore, you might not even receive them at the point when the task was assigned to you. In this case, you’ll need to list of the data and platforms you require for the analysis and work with the administrator to obtain access to them. First information required is definitely the email alerts sent via the control tower during the stipulated period. If data is appended in the email alert, you might also require the attachment(s) as well. Depending on how long you’ve been with the team and organisation, you may or may not know who to reach out to. Hence, there is a need to clarify with your manager or senior(s) who have previous experience working on similar analysis.</p> <p>You would also need access to the data sources of the control tower in question. This is so that you can extract, transform and analyse the underlying data in order to assess the accuracy of the alerts. If you don’t already have access, then you might need to find a channel that could grant access to the data sources, or help in extracting the relevant data points for your analysis.</p> <p>Depending on the size of the data, you may want to choose an appropriate platform for data cleaning and analysis. In most established organisation, this might also require approval to run analysis and allocation of compute resources.</p> <h3 id="3-analysis">3. Analysis</h3> <p>Finally, you’ve reached the part on analysis - the bread and butter of a data analyst role. However, you find yourself questioning what each of the attribute in the data really mean. This is especially true when you are working in an unfamiliar domain area. Perhaps, it good to ask whether there is a channel where you can find relevant metadata information?</p> <p>In the event if data points don’t tally, what are some of the possible reasons? Is there additional filter or exceptions that should be considered? Further clarification with the stakeholders might be required to deep dive into the initial design and objective of the alerts, and clarify if there is any subsequent change to the logic of triggering the alert. Sometimes there are just too much unknown and uncertainty for you to come to a conclusion with the available data. There could be blind spots that you are just not aware of. However, close communications and collaboration with the stakeholders would ensure that most of the uncertainties are clarified and addressed during the analysis phase.</p> <p>If the data couldn’t tell a conclusive story, you may want to highlight that the current data is insufficient to provide conclusive evidence for the problem and suggest ways or additional data points that could be collected for the analysis to proceed further.</p> <h3 id="summary">Summary</h3> <p>Each task and problem is unique in nature. The steps to take may differ from problem to problem. However, one can certainly build up experience in structured thinking over time and start asking the right questions after thinking through the problem. This would save so much time and effort that could be a result of misaligned expectations and insufficient communications and collaboration with the relevant parties.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="soft-skills"/><category term="structured-thinking"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ability to think through problem, break them down and figure out a way to find out more and understand them using data.]]></summary></entry></feed>